Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Hills Association records, 1924-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Hills Association records 1924-1995, 1940-1995
Ann Arbor Hills Association.
4 linear feet
85615 Cc 2
Ann Arbor neighborhood association. Correspondence, constitution, bylaws, minutes, financial records, and other working papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Elizabeth Brown (Donor No. 3290 ) on behalf of the organization in 1965. Periodic additions have been received.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open for research use.
The Ann Arbor Hills Association (AAHA) was founded in 1924. Ann Arbor Hills is a prime residential area within the City of Ann Arbor, Michigan, lying roughly between Washtenaw Avenue on the west and south, and Huron Hills golf course on the north and east. Some 150 homes lie within the Ann Arbor Hills area.
The AAHA was founded for several purposes: to protect property values of homes within Ann Arbor Hills; to represent the interests of Association members in assuring effective services from the City of Ann Arbor, including such things as police and fire protection, traffic control, water and sewage services, and public education; and to beautify the area of Ann Arbor Hills through the cooperative volunteer action of its members, thus enhancing its attractiveness as an exclusive residential area within the City of Ann Arbor.
The AAHA has been vigilant in the pursuit of its purposes. Starting in 1948, the Building Committee records attest to the association's intent to assure compliance with their restrictions by careful monitoring of all real estate transactions, new building construction, and property modifications, to protect the value of all homes in the AAHA area. The AAHA maintains surveillance of all city services provided to its members, dealing over the years with such issues as major sewage problems (lasting a decade), a spate of silver theft requiring the attention of the Ann Arbor Police Department, problem traffic areas, better street lighting at key intersections, the establishment of a Recycling Collection Station within the Association's boundaries, and the formation of a Neighborhood Watch Program.
The AAHA takes very seriously its purpose to protect the value of its homes. Debate with the City Planning Commission over annexation to the City of Ann Arbor occupied the association between 1952 and 1963. Beginning in 1959, and spanning twelve years, the Padover Proposal concerned the AAHA'a struggle to restrict zoning within its neighborhood boundaries. In the 1970s and early 1980s the Association took legal action against several of its residents/members (every homeowner in Ann Arbor Hills is a member of the Association by virtue of that ownership). Some of the lawsuits concerned what the association considered improper use of residential property. The Robey and Spindler files concern members taken to court by the Association for attempting to establish private psychological practices in their homes. The Broomfield/Pollard file covers two years of correspondence and legal measures concerning the occupancy of a house during an academic leave of absence by people the association considered undesirable.
The decade of the 1980s was filled with intense activity for the AAHA. Property issues related to disposal and development occupied much of the association's attention. The association was as determined to exclude certain groups and activities from the Ann Arbor Hills area as it was to promote improvements and development according to specific standards within its restrictive covenants. The Cora Shoecraft property successfully became a park. Equally successful in its own way was the opposition to a half-way house and to the construction of sidewalks in Ann Arbor Hills.
Two issues dominate the history of the AAHA in the mid-1980s: the Bader School Property and the Huron Parkway intersection with the Ann Arbor Hills area. From contention regarding its closure, to energetic concern about its disposal, its eventual sale and the AAHA's subsequent wrangling with the purchaser, the Fellowship Bible Church, the Bader School Property consumed the association's attention from 1984-1991. The association's battle with the city over Huron Parkway began in 1959, continued through 1964, and re-emerged in 1983 with the proposed sale of the Mills Property.
The records of the Ann Arbor Hills Association (AAHA) document the association's interests, concerns and general business. These records have survived and been sent to the Bentley Historical Library by Mrs. Elizabeth (Betty) Brown, one of the association's long-standing members and secretary for several decades. Perusal of the records will reveal the intricate intertwining of the association's life with that of Mrs. Brown.
The records have been divided into three series. Each series has been organized alphabetically, for the most part. Within sub-series the records may reflect subject organization rather than alphabetical or chronological organization. The 1996 accession has not been described in detail.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Hills Association.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Homeowners' associations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Hills (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
- History and Background Materials 1924-1987 (scattered dates)
  History and Background Materials comprise the first series, with items covering the years between 1924 and 1987. In these folders will be found an introductory brochure, a map, and various legal documents, including incorporation documents (1925-1961), Articles of Constitution (1924-1987), and charter renewal materials (1955, 1984).
  - Introductory Brochure (Box 1)
    (contains historical information and maps)
  - Organizational Documents
    - Incorporation Documents and Deeds 1925, 1945-1950 (Box 1)
    - Legal Agreements 1925-1961 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Articles/By-Laws 1924-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Charter Renewal 1955-1984 (Box 1)
- Administration 1924-1988
  The association's administrative business comprises the second series. This Administration series has six sub-series: 1.) all material dealing with the Annual Meetings, 1924-1988 (minutes, reports, call to meetings, agendas, membership lists); 2) business from the Board of Directors 1926, scattered dates 1941-1988 (correspondence and minutes); 3) voluminous correspondence and business records of the Building Committee from 1948-1983; 4) various financial matters including yearly audits (1947-1972); 5) general correspondence of the association with several items from 1925 and 1931, but the bulk covering the years 1940-1988 with several large gaps (1932-1939, 1964, and 1966-1972); and 6) newsletters of the association, 1946-1988 (missing issues from 1955-56 and 1969-1971).
  - Annual Meetings
    - Call to Meeting 1925-1979 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Agendas 1958-1987 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1924-1948, 1945-1952 (scattered dates), 1958-1975 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1978-1987 (Box 1)
    - Officers and Committee Members 1955-1980 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Proxy Forms (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Beautification Committee 1982-1987 (Box 1)
      - Building Committee 1947, 1955-1986 (Box 1)
      - Financial Summaries 1964-1986 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
      - Liaison Committee with City of Ann Arbor 1965-1987 (Box 1)
      - Membership Lists 1931, 1945, 1950-1988 (Box 1)
      - Recycling Committee 1980-1986 (Box 1)
      - Schools Committee 1960-1985 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
      - Special Zoning Committee 1962 (Box 1)
      - Welcoming and Membership Committee 1962 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - Correspondence 1926, 1965-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1941-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Building Committee
    - Correspondence 1958-1983, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Blueprints 1960-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Finance
    - Audits 1947-1972 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's record 1949-1962 (Box 1)
    - Monthly Accounts 1979-1985 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Accounts 1927-1971 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Tax Rates 1925-1956 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1925-1988, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - 1946-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1988 (Box 1)
- Topical Files 1951-1989
  The Topical Files in series is composed of seven major files. Most of this material is correspondence, but news clippings and speeches also exist. The Ann Arbor 2000 file demonstrates the association's eagerness to be a part of city planning and events.
  The Bader School Property file (1984-1991) contains records documenting the AAHA's concern over the closing of Bader School and its eventual sale to Fellowship Bible Church. Of the six Bader School folders, three folders contain correspondence related to the school's closure and sale. One folder contains news clippings pertinent to the sale, and one folder contains public speeches and statements about the sale by association members. The last folder in this sub-series contains the tense exchange of correspondence between the AAHA and the Fellowship Bible Church.
  The Community Concerns file (7 folders) deals with covenants, safety issues and improvements to the Ann Arbor Hills area. A large number of folders focus on covenants: relationships, restrictions, disputes and litigation taken by the association against its own members. The association constantly surveyed its own members' development and use of their property, and maintained strict control over the neighborhood through rigorous restrictions promptly communicated and exercised. The second folder in this section holds correspondence dealing with a dispute among two residents: Carpenter and Weaver (1961). The litigation file contains correspondence and legal documents concerning members who refused to comply with AAHA restrictions. By far the most significant of these is the Robey file (1968-1981), followed by the Broomfield/Pollard file (1980-1982). Not all the association's members appreciated the AAHA's readiness to take its own members to court. Some members protested by requesting termination of their membership in the association. This correspondence is in the Neighborhood Relations file (1948-1988, scattered dates).
  Other Community Concerns were issues such as traffic control and intersections (Sheridan/Manchester, 1982), the development of a Neighborhood Watch (1977-1983), the resistance to sidewalks (1986), and objections to a half-way house (1988-1989). Two major property improvements took place: the Cora Shoecraft Park (1980-1984), and the Tuomy Hills Gas Station (1987-1988).
  The Hubbard/Duffus Correspondence has been extracted from general correspondence for reasons of interest. This correspondence spans two generations of a family and concerns the story of one family living in the Ann Arbor Hills area of the city (1946-1985).
  The Huron Parkway file documents the Association's efforts to prevent construction of the Huron Parkway on or near Ann Arbor Hills. The three major components of this file have been arranged in a partially chronological fashion, inasmuch as the dates overlap: Exmoor By-Pass [3 folders] (1959-1986), Western Access [2 folders] (1964), and Mills Property [1 folder] (1983-1986).
  The Padover Proposal covered a lengthy process of objection and negotiation regarding residential use of property versus commercial and business use of the same property. The file covers the years 1959-1971.
  The file on Planning Commission issues documents one smaller concern of Land Use Control (1971-1972), and three larger issues for the association: Annexation (1952-1963), Sewage (1951-1959) and Water (1951-1958).
  - Ann Arbor 2000, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Bader School Property
    - Sale 1984-1987, 3 files (Box 2)
    - News clippings 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Hills Association Reactions (Box 2)
  - Community Concerns (covenants, safety, improvements, etc.)
    - Covenants
      - Neighborhood Relations 1948-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
      - Disputes: Carpenter and Weaver 1961 (Box 2)
      - Litigation Against Individuals
        - Broomfield/Pollard 1980-1982 (Box 2)
        - Kincaid 1971 (Box 2)
        - Robey 1968-1981
          - Miscellaneous, 2 files (Box 2)
          - Legal Fees 1978-1980 (Box 2)
        - Spindler 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - Restrictions (animals) 1975 (Box 2)
    - Fire and Insurance Matters (Box 2)
    - Half-Way House 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Intersection of Sheriden/Manchester 1982 (Box 2)
    - Neighborhood Watch 1977-1983 (Box 2)
    - Property Improvements
      - Cora Shoecraft Park 1980-1984 (Box 2)
      - Tuomy Hills Gas Station 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Sidewalks 1986 (Box 2)
    - Traffic Speed Control 1952 (Box 2)
  - Hubbard Duffus Correspondence 1946-1985 (Box 2)
  - Huron Parkway
    - Exmoor By-Pass
      - 1959, 1964, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 2)
      - News clippings 1964, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Western Access
      - Planning Commission Meetings 1964 (Box 2)
      - Final Hearing 1964 (Box 2)
    - Mills Property 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Padover Proposal 1959-1971 (Box 2)
  - Planning Commission Issues
    - Annexation 1952-1963 (Box 2)
    - Land Use Control 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Sewage
      - General 1951-1959 (Box 2)
      - Special Assessments 1967 (Box 2)
    - Water 1951-1958 (Box 2)
- Later records (1996 accession)
  - Historical and chronological materials 1978-1995 (Box 3)
  - Halfway house/Coalition for Responsible Prison Site Selection 1989-1991 (Box 4)
  - Litigation (Box 4)